S2 Module 2: The Sum-Check Protocol with Justin Thaler
Justin: Hi, I'm Justin Thaler.
I'm an associate professor at Georgetown
and a research partner at a16z.
Going to talk about the Sum-Check Protocol today.
Tracy: Cool.
I'm Tracy.
I'm co-founder of Pluto.
I've been working with zk-SNARKs for app devs.
Justin: All right. So the topic
today is the Sum-Check Protocol,
which is due to Lund, Fortnow,
Karloff, and Nisan from way back
in the very early days of
Verifiable Computing, 1990 or so.
Now, this solves the following problem,
which probably looks a little
funny the first time you see it.
But the goal is to compute a
big sum of the following form.
So we're summing over n-bit inputs,
so x in ⁿ of g(x),
where g is some n-variate polynomial.
And the protocol is sort of going to be secure
and efficient only if g is "low degree."
Let's not worry right now what low degree means.
And from the verifier's perspective, the
Sum-Check Protocol is like a reduction.
This sum involves 2ⁿ terms. Right?
So the verifier could compute the sum on its own
by kind of evaluating g at 2ⁿ
points and summing it on its own.
The verifier is thinking, "oh, that's a lot
of work. I don't want to do that myself."
"I want the prover, who I don't
trust to do that work for me."
And so the verifier in the Sum-Check Protocol
will ultimately only have to
evaluate g at a single point.
But the wrinkle is that that
single point is a random point,
and the randomness is not just from .
It's from a much bigger space,
something called a finite field.
So again, so for the verifier,
Sum-Check Protocol reduces this very difficult
task of summing 2ⁿ evaluations of g,
to the task of just evaluating
g at a single point.
Albeit, a point from kind
of the whole field instead
of the -- what we call the "Boolean hypercube".
Tracy: Cool.
Justin: Any questions?
Tracy: Makes sense. I think it's great.
Justin: All right.
So hopefully we'll see kind of
why this protocol is so powerful,
why low degree polynomials sort of
make sense to arise in proof systems.
And so we're going to kind
of start at the beginning.
We're going to forget about the
Sum-Check Protocol for a little bit
and just talk about polynomials for a few minutes.
Okay.
So we've already seen that the
Sum-Check Protocol refers to
multivariate polynomials, n-variate polynomials.
But let me just go back to basics for a minute
and quickly talk about
univariate polynomials. Right?
So a degree d univariate polynomial is just
a sum of coefficients times
associated power of the one input.
So this is a degree d univariate
polynomial that I just wrote.
Tracy: It's like the classic
linear combination of terms.
Justin: Exactly.
And this is called the standard monomial basis.
These coefficients are
coefficients of powers of x.
There are other bases that
also make sense to think about,
as we'll see for the Sum-Check Protocol,
it's the "Lagrange basis" that makes more sense,
but kind of starting at with what
people should be most comfortable with.
Univariate polynomial of degree d
in the standard monomial basis.
Okay.
And a basic fact, I always forget if this
is the fundamental theorem of algebra
or something from kind of 8th grade or 9th grade,
but if p and q are two distinct,
so they're not the same degree
(at most) d polynomials,
okay, then they have to
disagree at almost all inputs.
So that means then p(x) = q(x)
for at most --
So a line -- two lines that are not
the same, can agree at one point.
So d points. They can agree at d points.
Great.
So this is another way of saying this
is just a reformulation of the fact that
any non zero degree d
polynomial has at most d roots.
Right?
Because p(x) = q(x) is equivalent
to like (p-q)(x) = 0.
So talking about agreement points
of p and q is like the same as
talking about roots of p minus q.
Tracy: Right.
So if they share roots, they'll
agree on all those points,
but everywhere else they'll be different.
Justin: Yes. Exactly.
This is almost the only fact you need
to design efficient interactive proofs.
Even though interactive proofs
use multivariate polynomials,
kind of each round of the interaction
involves a univariate one.
So you really only ever for the most
part apply this univariate fact.
There is a multivariate analog of this
fact called the Schwartz–Zippel lemma,
which might come up later in this session.
But anyway, this is for the
most part all you need to know.
So nothing beyond 8th grade.
Tracy: Cool.
Justin: Great.
So that's univariate polynomials.
But as already mentioned, the Sum-Check
Protocol uses multivariate polynomials.
And so it is helpful to introduce the
notion of multilinear polynomials.
Now, you don't need to know
about multilinear polynomials
to understand the Sum-Check Protocol,
but you do typically need them
to understand applications of it.
Typically, the polynomials
that Sum-Check gets applied to
are kind of built out of
several multilinear polynomials.
So in order to understand how the Sum-Check
gets applied, we do need to discuss this.
So this is just let's say n-variate polynomials
of degree at most one in each variable.
Okay.
So an example of a multilinear polynomial,
let's say in three variables,
x₁, x₂, and x₃ would be,
let's say 3 * x₁ * x₂ * x₃ + x₁ * x₂.
Okay. But if I were to add in a term x1
squared, it would not be multilinear anymore.
Okay.
Tracy: Because that term is not linear.
Justin: Yeah. Because of the exponent
of 2 in a -- for a single variable.
You know this --
You know, if the exponent was 3,
it would also not be multilinear.
So as long as you look at each variable
and its exponent is 1 in every
single term, you're multilinear.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: Okay.
Now while we're talking about
multilinear polynomials,
we might as well also talk about what
are called multilinear extensions.
Okay.
And here the motivation for what
I'm about to describe comes from
the fact that the Sum-Check Protocol was computing
a sum over inputs in the
Boolean hypercube ⁿ.
Okay.
So let me draw like just a
2-variate polynomial here.
So say --
Okay. So, right --
Yeah. There we go.
So forget about poly --
Forget about polynomials for a second.
Let's just say we have a function
whose domain is  * .
So there's only four possible
inputs to the function.
And its outputs live in some finite field.
But just think of its outputs as numbers,
if you're not comfortable with fields,
integers or something.
Okay. So let me draw a picture of f here.
So let's say I map 0,0 to 2, 0,1
to 3, 1,0 to 4, and 1,1 to 5.
Okay. So if you give me any function
whose domain is the Boolean hypercube,
so, ⁿ for any n, here n is 2,
there always exists a unique
multilinear polynomial
that has the same behavior as the function
when you look at the polynomial
only over the hypercube.
Remember, you can evaluate the
polynomials outside the hypercube,
but this function we're "extending"
is defined only over the hypercube.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: Okay.
So there's just a unique multilinear extension.
This means a multilinear polynomial p,
such that p(x) = f(x)
for all x where f is defined,
which is the Boolean hypercube.
So I can draw the multilinear
extensions evaluations in this example.
So whereas f only has four
inputs, to p I can feed --
You know, for each of its two
variables, I can feed any field element.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: So the number of p is like extending
the number of rows from 2 to field size
and extending the number of
columns from 2 to field size.
So if this field has size
like 2^128 or something,
there's like, the rows just go, go,
go, go, go for like almost forever.
Tracy: So the goal is almost to reduce the
evaluation domain down to this smaller domain?
Justin: So I would --
If you start with f, which has the small domain,
the goal of p is to extend the
domain of f to the big one.
Tracy: I see.
Okay.
Justin: If you started with p and went to
f, you'd be reducing the domain from p to --
Tracy: Yeah.
I guess I'm thinking of this.
This has like the full domain of the field,
and this has the narrow domain, which -- yeah.
Justin: Yeah. Yeah.
So typically the functions we care about,
that we want to use Sum-Check
to compute or something,
are defined over the Boolean
domain, over the small domain.
And the reason we want to deal with polynomials
is for distance amplification purposes.
So roughly, if any two functions defined over
the hypercube differ at even a single evaluation,
their multilinear extensions, well, are distinct.
And so that there are two different low
degree polynomials that are not the same,
so they disagree almost
everywhere over the big domain.
Tracy: That makes sense.
Justin: So it's a distance amplification thing.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: So I wrote this, so it's
really easy to actually write out,
figure out what the multilinear
extension kind of looks like.
So in any direction it's linear, right?
So if you go from 2 to 4, the difference is 2.
So if you go one more step, it's 6.
If you go another step, it's 8 and so forth.
Similarly, 3 to 5, this one is 2. So 7 and 9 --
And then going in this direction,
2 to 3, one step is 2 to 3.
So if I go another step, I have 4.
If I go another step, I have 5, and so forth.
So going left to right, you go up
1, and top to bottom you go up 2.
That's the multilinear extension.
Tracy: I see. Okay.
Justin: Now note, any
function over the small domain
has many polynomials that extend
it, but only one is multilinear.
Okay.
So for this particular example,
I'll actually just write out an
expression for the multilinear extension
and then give you another
extension that's not multilinear.
Maybe we'll do one quick example after that
and then we're ready for Sum-Check.
Okay.
So for this picture, the multilinear
extension can be written as follows.
This is --
What I'm going to do is a procedure
called Lagrange interpolation,
although that fact doesn't matter.
So --
All right. This function maps input 0,0 to 2.
Tracy: Yep.
Justin: Okay.
So the first term --
Tracy: So what you're trying to
do is say, given this domain,
I'm going to create a polynomial
that fits these evaluations,
or that evaluates this domain.
Justin: Exactly.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: So --
Yeah. So in order to make sure
that the polynomial map 0,0 to 2,
I'm going to have a 2 * (1-x₁) * (1-x₂)
Tracy: So you're making this a root.
Justin: Well, what we're doing is without
the 2, this sort of picks out input 0,0.
Tracy: I see.
Okay. Yeah.
Justin: So 0,0 maps to 1
and any other Boolean input.
Tracy: All right. It's like switching.
You're essentially saying,
I'm going to switch 2 on.
So this is 2 on, essentially.
And then you're going to
write it again to switch 3 on.
Justin: Yeah, yeah.
So this just sort of turns input
0,0 on and everything else off.
And then 2 means multiplied by 2 gives you 2.
Tracy: Gives you 2.
Justin: And then if I want to turn input
0,1 on, I'm going to multiply that by 3.
So I got 1-x₁ to make sure 0 is on.
Tracy: Yep.
Justin: Times x₂ to make sure 1 is on.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: And then we have 4 * x₁ * (1-x₂),
which turns 1,0 on and maps it to 4.
And then finally 5 * x₁ * x₂, which turns, 1,1 on.
Tracy: Got it. Okay.
Justin: Yeah.
So that's Lagrange interpolation.
But just to be clear, so this is
the unique multilinear polynomial
that extends this 2-variate function f.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: But I can add things to --
If I don't want it to be multilinear,
I can add all sorts of things to it
and preserve the behavior
over the small domain. Right?
So I can add in like x₁ * (1-x₁)
and over the small domain, nothing changed
because this evaluates to 0 over the small domain.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: Right.
x1 equals 0 kills this. x₁
equals 1 also kills this.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: So there's sort of an infinite
number of non multilinear extensions,
but only there's exactly one
multilinear extension of anything.
Tracy: Interesting. Okay.
Justin: Great.
And again, so the reason these extension
polynomials are so useful in proof systems is
because it's like if the prover
lies about any little thing it did,
you need the verifier to pick up on the lie.
So we need little teeny differences
between something that's perfectly right
and something that's off by a little to
get blown up into huge differences.
And so again, like if you
took two different functions
over the small domain that
differ even a single input,
their multilinear extensions are
going to differ almost everywhere.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: So if you look at them at
a random point, they'll differ.
Tracy: Yeah. Got it.
Justin: Okay.
And just so one example --
Tracy: And the goal really here --
Sorry to interrupt.
The goal really here is to prove that the --
Is for the verifier to be able to demonstrate that
the prover has used this polynomial
throughout all of its operations.
Justin: Ultimately, that's kind
of what happens in the SNARKs.
And we'll see as we see applications of
Sum-Check that will become much, much clearer.
Tracy: Okay.
And maybe one thing I wanted to
understand, so this makes sense,
like it's captured this domain.
Is this the multilinear extension?
Like and is adding these
additional terms extending this?
Justin: Oh no. When you add non multilinear
terms, you still have an extension,
meaning it has the right
behavior over the small domain.
Tracy: Correct.
Justin: But it's not multilinear anymore.
So this right here, without any --
This is the multilinear extension of the fs that
map 0,0 to 2, 0,1 to 3, 1,0 to 4 and 1,1 to 5.
This is it. This is multilinear.
Tracy: Okay. Got it.
Justin: There are other extensions
that are not multilinear.
Tracy: I understand. Okay.
Okay. Cool.
Justin: Great. And now, so
I'll just do one more example.
It's a really important one. I
call it the equality function.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay. So here, this is going to take --
This is -- take two inputs, say x and y.
So eq(x, y), where both
of them are in ⁿ.
Okay. And it's going to spit out --
So we're defining eq to spit out 1 if x
and y are the same vectors and 0 otherwise.
Tracy: I see. Okay.
Justin: Okay. And so the multilinear extension --
Tracy: So it's going to take a different form
from this, which enforces this characteristic.
Justin: Right. Right. Exactly.
So note like the number of terms --
When I did Lagrange interpolation, the
number of terms was 2ⁿ. Right?
There was one term for every
input in the small domain.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: We're going to see that eq can actually be
evaluated in its multilinear extension in time n.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: Okay.
So basically, if you have really nice functions,
you can evaluate them faster
than going like term by term
through this Lagrange interpolation definition.
So --
By the way, whenever I have a
function over the small domain
and I want to refer to its
multilinear extension polynomial,
I just stick a twiddle over it.
So this is not a polynomial.
It's just a function defined
over that Boolean hypercube.
If I stick a twiddle over it, it's a polynomial.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: And so --
Yeah, so let's say the inputs
here are like x₁ to xₙ, y₁ to yₙ.
Okay. So what is this?
So --
I'm just going to write it and then
we'll explain why this equality is true.
So we have xi -- so it's a product of n things
where the "i" thing is xᵢ*yᵢ + (1-xᵢ) * (1-yᵢ).
Okay?
So let's call this a claim, if you will. Because
I haven't explained why this is true yet.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay.
So to see why it's true, you
just have to check two things.
One, check that the right-hand
side is a multilinear polynomial.
And it is. Right?
Because everything has degree 1.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Yeah. The --
Any two terms of the product involve different
variables. So no variable has degree 2.
So all we have to do to confirm that it is the
multilinear extension of this equality function
is make sure that if you feed in
any two Boolean vectors x and y,
this polynomial spits out
whatever equality it spits out.
Tracy: Yeah. I see.
Justin: Okay. So what's happening here
is we're going over each and every bit.
Tracy: So the outcome of this is always 0 or 1.
Justin: Yes.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: And so the i-th term is just checking,
is the i-th bit of x equal to the i-th bit of y.
Right. If they're both 1, then this spits
out 1, and this spits out 0, and you get 1.
If they're both 0, then this
spits out 0, and this spits out 1.
And if one is 0 and the other is
1, then both these terms are 0.
And so producting them together is
saying for every i, does xᵢ equal yᵢ?
That's equality.
Tracy: Yeah.
It's just a way of encoding
equality checks into a polynomial.
Justin: Yeah. Exactly.
Tracy: To a multilinear --
Justin: Exactly --
Tracy: Extended polynomial.
Justin: Exactly.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: So this is a --
This comes up in lots of applications
of the Sum-Check Protocol.
And you know, there are other nice examples
just to get comfortable with it.
If I just had 2 --
Tracy: Is this the equality check, I guess?
Is that what it's called, or?
I guess it ladders up to
an equality check somehow.
Justin: Yeah. The equality --
So this is especially useful --
well, it's useful all over the place,
but definitely comes up in what we
call zerochecks, but we'll see soon.
Basically, zerochecks mean you want
to checkd: does everything equal zero?
Tracy: I see.
Justin: So you test equality
with zero sort of thing. Yeah.
Just one last example,
I guess if I want to compute the OR, of
just two inputs like x₁, y₁, that is --
the multilinear extension of that
is x₁ + y₁ - x₁ * y₁.
And you can just -- you know, you can --
there are only four possible inputs to it.
You can just --
Tracy: If you go through the
table, then this plays out.
Justin: Yeah. Yeah.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: Yeah. So there are other
simple ones that are good to look at,
You know, XOR, AND -- just get comfortable with it
Okay. So that's just getting comfortable
with multivariate polynomials
and multilinear ones in particular.
And now we're ready for the Sum-Check Protocol.
Tracy: All right.
Justin: Okay.
So let's see how the Sum-Check Protocol works
and then we'll see some applications of it.
So remember, the goal in the
Sum-Check Protocol is to compute
the sum over all x in ⁿ of g(x) for
some "low degree" polynomial g and n variables.
Again, we'll see applications where
then you'll know what this g is.
However, I will mention that
in most SNARK applications,
the number of terms in the sum
you should think of as roughly --
So terms being summed, you should think of as like
the size of the circuit that the
prover is making a claim about.
So there's like one term in the
sum for every gate in the circuit
or one term in the sum for every
constraint in your constraint system,
which means little n, the number of
variables, is log of size of circuit
or number of constraints or whatever.
Tracy: Right. Okay. So we have
a circuit of length 2ⁿ.
Justin: Yes. Yeah.
And so, remember in Sum-Check, there will
be as we'll see one round per variable.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay. Which means in SNARK applications,
one round -- like log circuit size many rounds.
Which means in Sum-Check-based SNARKs,
the verifier is roughly going
to run in log circuit size time.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: Which is actually pretty good.
You know, there's a lot of poly logs
out there that are much more than log,
like logic cubed.
Tracy: This is kind of reminiscent of FRI to me.
We're going to kind of reduce the amount of
work over time by doing log n rounds of work.
Justin: Yes. It's also
reminiscent of Bulletproofs.
And topic for another presentation, but
Bulletproofs literally is Sum-Check.
So if you know Bulletproofs, you
actually already know Sum-Check,
although you probably don't realize
that you already know Sum-Check.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: Okay.
So there's exactly, like the size
of the problem we're dealing with
it's going to halve in every round.
And in fact, every round, what it's going to
do is sort of split the problem into two halves
and take like a random combination of the two
halves to get a problem instance of half the size.
Tracy: Awesome.
Justin: Okay.
So at the start of the
protocol, kind of round zero,
the prover will send like a claimed answer, C₀.
And the verifier says, hey, prover,
I don't trust that you're honest.
Convince me that the claimed answer is C₀.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: And the prover is going to say, all right,
this is how I'm going to convince you. So --
Tracy: And there's a consistency check, right?
Justin: There will be a consistency check
between the prover's round one message,
which I'll define in a second,
and this claimed answer, C₀.
So I'll try not to forget the consistency check.
So the prover is going to
send a univariate polynomial,
let me call it s₁, and variable capital X₁.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Which if the prover's honest, it will
equal the following univariate polynomial.
So the honest polynomial, I'm going to call h₁.
But if the prover is cheating, it might
send an s₁ that's not equal to h₁.
So h1 will be defined as a
sum over slightly fewer terms.
So what we're going to do now is we're going
to sum over everything but the first variable.
So we're going to leave the first
variable sort of not summed over,
just a free variable,
but we are still going to sum over Boolean
values for the last n - 1 variables.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: Okay.
Now, this message is specifically designed
so that if the prover is honest, then --
You know, so if s₁ equals h₁,
then the following will hold.
So if s₁ equals what it should equal,
then the claimed answer will equal
or the true answer will equal
s₁(0) plus s₁(1). Right?
Because we define h₁ to just not
sum over that first variable.
If you then go back and sum over that first
variable, you should get out the actual answer.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: And again, when we said
that each round of Sum-Check
sort of takes the big problem
instance over 2ⁿ terms
and splits it into two halves and like takes
a random linear combination of the two halves,
these are the two halves.
So this is capturing the terms where x₁ is 0.
Right? If you feed 0 into h₁, that's
like feeding 0 in for the first variable.
And if you feed 1 in, it's like
feeding 1in for the first --
So those are the two halves where --
Tracy: So you split the
terms into two halves. I see.
Justin: Exactly.
And now to compare to like
Bulletproofs or maybe FRI is easier.
No. For both of them.
This is like the magic of Sum-Check.
For FRI or Bulletproofs, you split
the big thing into two halves
and the prover would
cryptographically commit to each half.
Here, there's no commitments,
there's no cryptography.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: So that's one of the
amazing things about Sum-Check
and why it's so key to fast prover SNARKs.
Tracy: So it doesn't need to
send a commitment to each half.
What does it send instead of a commitment?
Justin: So it just sends s₁. Okay?
Tracy: Which is a low degree polynomial.
Justin: Very low degree, and only in one variable.
So let's say just for concreteness
that g has degree 2 in each variable.
In most applications, g actually
will have degree, like 3,
sometimes 2, sometimes a little more than 3.
But let's say 2 in each variable for simplicity
Now note, like a univariate polynomial
of degree 2 only has three coefficients.
And so s₁ and h₁, they're
univariate polynomials of degree 2.
So the prover is just sending s
-- it's just 3 field elements.
It turns out, actually you don't even need
the prover to send all three field elements
because this check is only going to
pass if s₁(1) = C₀ - s₁(0).
So you don't even need the prover to send.
You can kind of get rid of a field element
by just inferring 1 degree of
freedom from this check passing.
Tracy: I got you.
Justin: If it were anything
else, the check would fail.
So just why not just assume it passes.
So very, very small messages in each round?
And there's one round per variable.
So the total proof size winds up
being like after the optimizations,
two log circuit size or something
like that, many field elements.
Tracy: I see.
So every round you're going
to pass over 2 field elements
it can do the evaluation then,
and then you're going to
repeat that for log n rounds?
Justin: Right. Exactly.
Now, the problem is, right now I've
only told you the round one message.
So why are we not like done? Right?
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: And the issue is the verifier
doesn't actually know what h₁ is. Right?
It's defined in terms of this pretty big sum,
which is like half the size of
the original sum, but still big.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: So it doesn't actually
know does s₁ equal h₁?
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Yeah.
So that is the purpose of
the next round. And so --
Tracy: It's checked sort of one constraint,
but it hasn't checked all of h₁.
Justin: That's right.
So the consistency check, which I
need to make sure not to forget,
is that after the prover sends s₁,
the verifier checks that s₁(0) + s₁(1)
indeed equals the claimed answer.
That's asking like are these two pieces
actually consistent with the original
claim that had just one piece.
And then the verifier needs to check
like, are these two pieces honest?
That is, does s₁ actually equal h₁?
Okay.
And now the prover explicitly
sent s₁ to the verifier.
It's just three coefficients.
And so the verifier actually knows
s₁. But the verifier does not know h₁.
Tracy: Right.
Justin: Okay. So how is the verifier going
to check this when it doesn't know h₁?
Well, let me make things a little simpler,
although it's not the end of the story.
The verifier is just going to pick a
random field element, a random input to s₁,
So sends that field element to --
let me call it r₁, to the prover.
Tracy: And it asks it to evaluate h₁ at that r₁.
Justin: Right. Right. And then, you know --
And now wants to confirm --
And this is what the round two is going to be
targeted at, that s₁(r₁) = h₁(r₁).
Now, the verifier on its own can
compute s₁(r₁). It knows s₁.
But it doesn't know h₁(r₁).
So it's going to use round two of
Sum-Check to try to compute h₁(r₁).
Tracy: And what this does is it
lets the verifier confirm that
this s1 is a univariate
polynomial of the larger whole.
Justin: It lets the prover confirm that
s1 actually equals what it should, h₁.
And if it does equal what it should,
then the claimed answer is indeed
correct by the consistency check.
Tracy: I see.
Okay.
Justin: Yeah. And this --
You know, there's a way to picture this as --
You know, we split the sum into two halves.
The first half is where the
first variable is fixed to 0,
and the second half is where the
first variable is fixed to 1.
And the fixing the first variable to r₁
is like taking a random linear
combination of the two halves sort of.
And so you sort of collapse the
two halves together into one.
Tracy: Fold them together.
Justin: Yeah. Fold them together.
And the key point here is that h₁(r₁) is --
Let me just stick r₁ in here. Right?
Is --
Well, it's exactly the kind of statement
we designed Sum-Check to prove,
except now we're applying it to a
polynomial with one fewer variable.
So rather than apply Sum-Check to G
itself, apply it to the polynomial --
Let me call it, I don't know,
g star of x₂ to xₙ obtained from g just
by fixing the first variable to r₁.
Tracy: Right. You reduce the problem a little bit.
Justin: Yeah. Exactly.
So you keep doing this round
over round, and then at the --
So after one round, variable
1 has been fixed to r₁.
So the prover is making -- you
know, proving the value of h₁(r₁),
which, remember, is like g of r₁ with other stuff.
After round two, the prover makes
a claim about like h₂(r₂),
which will be g with first variable
fixed r₁, the second variable fixed r₂.
And eventually you get to the nth
round, one round per variable.
And at the end of that round, the prover makes
a claim about g with all variables fixed.
And that claim, the verifier
is going to compute on its own
because we said the whole point of
Sum-Check is to reduce the original claim,
which involves 2ⁿ evaluations
of g, to evaluating g at a single point.
We've done that.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: But now we're going to have to talk about,
in applications, can the verifier actually
get that one evaluation quickly or not?
And that kind of varies. And
we'll talk about that more.
Tracy: Okay. Cool. It might be useful to
see how this kind of maps onto like an R1CS,
like a constraint system of some kind.
Justin: Great.
So that actually is the first
application I wanted to cover.
And we'll also make kind of
what's going on in the protocol,
I think, a little more concrete.
Let me leave this up here for now --
Actually, let --
Let me leave the goal up here.
And get rid of everything else.
Tracy: Sounds good.
Justin: Okay.
Maybe I'll start with the picture and then,
before I get a little more formal.
So in R1CS, there are three matrices
known to both prover and verifier.
They're called constraint matrices,
and they call them A, B and C.
Okay.
And the --
So these are matrices.
So maybe I'll say they have capital
M rows and capital N columns.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: And the prover claims
to know a z, such that (Az) --
So that's matrix-vector product,
entry wise, product (Bz) equals (Cz).
Tracy: Yep.
Justin: Okay.
Now I'm going to give these
matrix-vector products a name.
So let's say little a, little b and little c.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: Okay.
So the claim is that for every
constraint, every row of these matrices.
Tracy: This is effectively evaluating
the constraints of the SNARK
against a given witness and
finding it at 0 for all.
Justin: Yeah.
Tracy: All constraints.
Justin: So, yeah, you should think of z as like,
roughly the witness the SNARK
prover's claiming to know.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: And each row of these matrices
together makes one constraint.
And so the prover's claiming to know
a z that satisfies all M constraints.
And this capital N is like
the size of the witness,
and this capital M is the number of constraints.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay.
So the claim is that for every --
Every constraint is of the form ai --
Little aᵢ times little bᵢ equals little cᵢ.
So the claim is that for
every single entry of these,
this entry times this entry equals
-- minus this entry equals zero.
Tracy: Equals zero. Yeah.
Justin: Okay.
And so you have to do a little mental gymnastics.
Like, rather than thinking
of a as a vector of length m,
we want to think of it as a function
whose domain is 0,1 to the log m.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay. And this is a
very natural thing to do where
rather than indexing the elements of
a by integers between 0 and m minus 1,
we index them by bit vectors,
just the binary representations of the integers.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: So now we're going to ---
So we're viewing a as a function
whose domain is  to the log m.
Tracy: So there, if you look at
all combinations of bit vectors,
you can choose out of this, any given constraint.
Justin: Exactly.
So as a concrete example of size 4,
if this is a, we'd have a(0,0) = 2,
a(0,1) = 3, a(1,0) = 4, and a(1,1) = 5.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Right?
We're just indexing the entries of a
by bit vectors instead of integers.
Tracy: Yeah. So this is length 2ⁿ,
and as a result you have two
entries to index all of it.
Yeah.
Justin: Yeah. Exactly.
So, yeah, this has size capital M,
and the number of variables we're
feeding into a now is log of that.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Great.
And now the beautiful thing about
functions defined over  to the anything
is they always have a unique
multilinear extension.
So if I stick a twiddle over a, I mean, we're now
talking about as multilinear extension polynomial.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay. And so if you want
a Sum-Check-based SNARK for R1CS,
and there is one called Spartan,
essentially the first Sum-Check
is applied to a polynomial
and I'll tell you what it is in a -- momentarily,
that just captures this equality here,
But, you know, is replacing a, b and
c with their multilinear extensions,
because Sum-Check needs multivariate
polynomials to apply to.
Tracy: So you do a transformation,
get the multilinear extensions?
Justin: Right.
Tracy: And then you can
evaluate it with Sum-Check.
Justin: Right.
And so conceptually, what's going
to happen in the Sum-Check is
round one is going to kind of
split a, b and c into two halves
and make sure that the two
halves are consistent with
this right-hand side being zero as claimed.
And then just fold the two
halves on top of each other.
So round two, you're left with
three vectors of half the length.
And then round two --
Tracy: You do this by fixing one of the variables.
Justin: Yeah.
To a random value. Exactly.
So that's it.
And again, the benefit of
Sum-Check over a lot of the SNARKs
that actually are currently more popular today
is there's no commitment
costs in Sum-Check itself.
The prover is just like adding up
and multiplying field elements.
So if you compare to --
So like Marlin is a SNARK that does
not use multivariate polynomials,
it uses univariate ones and
it was described for R1CS.
So it --
Like it maps very cleanly into the same
setting as what we're talking about here.
And the very first thing Marlin will do is have
the prover commit to these vectors a, b and c.
Tracy: Yeah.
So you have to go through all n
terms to do the commitment. Yeah?
Justin: Right.
And committing to things is expensive,
and exactly how expensive it varies.
But certainly if you don't have to commit
to it, that's generally a good thing.
Tracy: I guess one difference
there is once you've committed,
you can do constant work in the verifier.
Justin: Right.
Tracy: Versus in Sum-Check, you're
doing log n work in the verifier.
Justin: Yes. Yes.
Yeah. So yeah, if you really want constant
size proofs, you really can't use Sum-Check.
You're always going to get log work.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: Okay.
But if you're going to have
sort of polylog-sized proofs
from using a hashing-based commitment
scheme like FRI or something,
you're going to have polylog anyway.
The log isn't really going to matter.
Tracy: Right.
And this gets more efficient than having
to commit all of that information.
Justin: Right, right.
And you don't really have to
check that the committed data,
you know, the more data you commit --
any data that's committed,
you ultimately have to prove that like the
data inside the commitment is like well formed.
So it's not just committing the data,
it's also proving that all that
extra committed data is like "kosher".
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Yeah. Then another nice thing is,
SNARKs that avoid multivariate
polynomials and just use univariate ones,
somewhere in the protocol there's typically
what's called a quotient polynomial.
And that quotient polynomial like, you might
or might not have to explicitly compute
that polynomial if you're the prover.
But with Sum-Check, there's --
there's just no -- there's no
quotienting. You're only ever summing,
You know, even if you don't
compute the quotient polynomial,
even if you don't commit to it,
the quotient polynomials values,
you kind of don't have any control over.
So even if all of the entries
in a, b and c are small,
once you have a quotient in there,
the values of the quotient get big.
And so, yeah, you just like have
fewer commitments and fewer divisions
and smaller values if you're
using this multivariate stuff.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: So wrapping up exactly
formally what happens in --
So this is --
I'm sketching the Spartan
kind of SNARK polynomial IOP.
I just do a quick --
This was why I introduced this equality polynomial
in sort of the first session of this presentation.
So I just need one basic fact about
polynomials, which is the following.
So let g(x) be any n-variate polynomial,
Let's say of --
I should leave it like that.
And not necessarily multilinear.
Just to be clear about that.
Okay. Let p(x) be the unique
multilinear polynomial that does this,
you know, agrees with g.
That is, has the same input output
behavior over Boolean inputs.
Remember, like I give you any input-output
behavior over the Boolean hypercube,
there's a unique multilinear polynomial
that has that behavior.
Okay?
Then we can express p, that's p(r).
You know, this is n variables in r as
the sum over x in ⁿ
of eq(x,r) * g(x). Okay?
All right.
So the way to check that this is true is
we did this once before when I
defined the equality polynomial.
You need to make sure that the
right-hand side is multilinear
and that it agrees with g at any r that's Boolean --
that only takes 0,1 coordinates.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: Okay.
And what's happening is it's
clearly multilinear because
we're only feeding r into this equality
thing, which is defined to be multilinear.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: And then to understand
its input output behavior, right?
Like if r only has 0,1 coordinates,
the whole point of eq is,
you're summing over all Boolean inputs,
but only one of them is going to equal r.
And so every term of the sum dies
except the one you care about,
and then you spit out g at that term.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay. So this is some kind
of multilinearization expression
where g might not be multilinear, but I can
sort of pretend it is by looking at this thing.
Tracy: Right. By just extracting one
piece of g and zeroing everything else.
Justin: Yeah. Something like that.
This is sort of taking like --
if r is chosen at random --
So ultimately the verifier will
choose r at random somewhere.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: Then this is taking some funny --
It's like summing up the
evaluations of g over the hypercube,
but each one is multiplied by some funny term.
And it's like, so if --
Yeah, and that's how you get rid of the
non-multilinear parts of g in that way.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: So yeah, the picture of how
Spartan works is what I told you before,
where you take a, b and c and sort of collapse
them in half, round over round over round.
But now I'm just going to fully tell
you the -- like, what do we actually --
What polynomial do we apply Sum-Check to?
Yeah.
So we just covered this fact
which let us express the evaluations
of the unique multilinear polynomial
that agrees with g over Boolean inputs
as a nice sum of evaluations of g.
Okay.
And so sums like this are exactly what
Sum-Check was designed to compute.
So I'm pretty happy that we were
able to describe the evaluations of p
in terms of the evaluations
of g in this sort of form.
Tracy: Right.
Justin: Okay.
So let's get back to Spartan and say
exactly what does it apply Sum-Check to?
So the polynomial g we wind
up caring about in Spartan is
the multilinear extension of a
times the multilinear extension
to b minus the multilinear extension to c.
Okay.
So what the prover's claiming --
You know, when the prover says that
the R1CS constraints are all satisfied,
that's equivalent to saying that g(x)=0
for all x in  to the log m.
Right?
You know, each x is indexing
like a constraint here.
And this is saying the x-th
constraint is satisfied.
Yeah. But g is not multilinear because
of the multiplication operation here.
Tracy: Yeah. I see.
Justin: Okay.
Now let's just take one more break and
observe that like, if g were multilinear,
it's not, but if it were multilinear,
okay, then this claim is equivalent
to g is the zero polynomial.
Because the zero polynomial is multilinear
and it has this behavior of all
points in the Boolean hypercube.
And that's unique.
Tracy: Right.
Justin: Okay.
So --
Tracy: So this is the technique you were
explaining of using the equality multilinear.
Justin: Exactly.
So if g were multilinear, it'd be enough for
the verifier to just pick a random point,
evaluate g at that point.
You know, if the provers honest, it'll spit out 0.
And if it's dishonest, g won't
be the zero polynomial, and it
won't spit out 0 with overrunning probability.
The problem is g is not multilinear.
That's what this is for.
Okay. So here's Spartan.
So V picks, you know, r in
field of the log m at random.
You know, sends r to the prover.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay.
And then they just apply
Sum-Check. Maybe r -- or r.
Yeah, apply Sum-Check to confirm that p(r)=0.
And what is p(r)?
So that is sum --
It's right over there. But x and  to
the log m, of eq twiddle (x,r) comma g(x).
Okay. And --
Great. So that's what Spartan does.
Tracy: Awesome.
Justin: Now, at the end of this Sum-Check,
the verifier has to evaluate this
polynomial at a random point.
Which requires evaluating g at a random point.
Tracy: Yep.
Justin: Okay. Now that is a little bit annoying
because the verifier doesn't know what
little a, little b, and little c are.
Tracy: Right.
Justin: Okay.
But it turns out you can get the one
evaluation of each of these that you need
with the second Sum-Check.
Tracy: Interesting.
Justin: Okay.
And at the end of the second Sum-Check,
the verifier winds up having to
evaluate just z at a random point.
And this z would have been committed
at the start of the protocol
with a scheme that would let the
evaluation come from the commitment scheme.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: And so, yeah, the
nice thing about Spartan,
relative to SNARKs that don't use Sum-Check,
that only use univariate polynomials,
is only z is getting committed.
Not little a, little b, little c.
There's no quotient polynomials.
Tracy: You're committing the witness, but
you're not required to commit the full circuit.
Justin: Yeah.
Like not the value for every
constraint, just the witness.
And you kind of -- yeah.
Yeah.
Tracy: Which reduces the provers work.
Justin: Yeah.
And in fact, it's now known that the prover in
this Sum-Check can be brought
down to 5 m field operations.
That 5 is, like really small.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Like Nothing else really matches that.
So it uses some optimizations
that are very recent,
but even before those it was 10 m or something.
So, yeah, there's just like --
5 m field ops is like nothing relative
to most of SNARKs that are used today.
Yeah.
So that's Spartan.
Tracy: Cool. And I guess we're
going to talk a little bit about GKR
and maybe contrast some of these techniques --
this technique specifically with some
other techniques that exist for SNARKs.
Justin: Yes. Exactly.
So Spartan is one Sum-Check-based
SNARK, and GKR is --
Well, it's actually an interactive
proof that uses Sum-Check Protocol
that you can turn into a SNARK by
combining it with a commitment scheme.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: And I think it's
instructive to compare the two
because GKR is kind of taking the
Sum-Check ethos to an extreme,
like really, really, really minimizing
the amount of committed data.
Which is really powerful in certain applications,
but can come with downsides in others.
So we can talk about that a bit.
Tracy: Okay
Justin: Okay.
So the GKR Protocol,
named for Goldwasser, Kalai, and
Rothblum, who introduced it in 2008,
is sort of best described in the
context of circuits rather than R1CS.
So this is just like the inputs
to the circuit are field elements
and the gates of the circuit, each gate sort of
adds or multiplies two field elements together.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay.
Tracy: It's more reminiscent of Plonk than R1Cs.
Justin: Right. So Plonk was originally
described for circuits as well.
And if you applied Spartan to a
circuit, we described it for R1CS,
but you can apply it naturally to a circuit.
In fact, that's basically an
earlier work called Clover.
The very first thing the prover would do is
cryptographically commit to the
value of every gate in the circuit.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: Okay. And then Spartan just has like two Sum-Checks.
Okay.
And actually, in applications like
Jolt, you only need one Sum-Check.
So it's kind of proving the
whole circuit all at once.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Okay.
In the GKR Protocol, the prover
never commits to anything.
The verifier does need to ultimately evaluate
the input to the circuit at a random point.
It's multilinear extension.
And so if the verifier knows
x, the input to the circuit,
there's no cryptography in the GKR Protocol.
Tracy: Got it.
Justin: It's an interactive proof.
There's no committing to anything.
It's information theoretically sound.
Tracy: Right. So contrasting that to FRI or KZG,
both make cryptographic commitments which
depend on different cryptographic constructions.
Justin: Right.
And so, you know, any SNARK
is typically obtained by
combining a polynomial IOP and
a polynomial commitment scheme.
And FRI and KZG are the commitment
schemes. They're examples of them.
And so Spartan would also need
a commitment scheme like that
and any commitment scheme, like if
you can compute a discrete logarithm,
if you're an attacker and you
can compute discrete logarithms,
or if you can like find
collisions and hash functions,
you can break binding of the commitment scheme,
and therefore, find convincing proofs
of false statements in the SNARK.
Tracy: Right.
Justin: Okay.
GKR, if the verifier knows the
input to the circuit, there just --
There's no cryptography, so there's no hash
function for the adversary to try to break.
You know, the adversary could
take trillions of years.
And if you run the protocol interactively anyway,
the security is coming from the fact that
in round i of the Sum-Check Protocol,
when the prover sends its degree 3 polynomial,
it does not know the random point rᵢ,
that the verifier is going to pick in
that round to like check its claim at.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: So in the Sum-Check Protocol,
it's like the security is coming from
non-predictability of the verifier challenge,
and there's no security coming from it.
There's no cryptography hash
functions groups anywhere.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: Now, in SNARK applications,
often the verifier won't know x,
and so x will be committed,
but the gates of the circuit
values don't have to be committed.
Tracy: And one of the appeals of that is that the
amount of work that the prover needs to
do is linear instead of being n log n.
Justin: Yeah. So it depends what
commitment scheme we're talking about
to discuss how expensive would these
commitments be if we did commit.
But generally speaking, like the field operations
that the Sum-Check prover does are cheaper.
Like group operations are built
out of field operations. Right?
And if you avoid groups, you're going
to have to do things like hashes or FFTs
and like one hash or --
it's all just much more expensive than
adding or multiplying two field elements.
Tracy: Right.
Justin: That's the intuition.
And now everything is very complicated in
practice, but that's roughly what's happening.
The downside of having no commitments at all,
even if the verifier does know
x, there can be downsides,
is it can be pretty hard or
impossible to keep the circuit small.
So there are general techniques
for keeping circuits small
so that we apply SNARKs to small
circuits instead of huge circuits,
uses a lot of untrusted advice.
And this means, if you need
to divide two quantities,
rather than having the circuit
literally run a division algorithm,
we have the prover provide
the quotient and remainder,
and the circuit just checks that they're correct
with like, one multiplication, one addition.
Now, if there's no commitment scheme,
that untrusted advice either has to
be sent explicitly to the verifier.
But fortunately, a lot of the circuits
we wind up caring about in SNARK design,
they're very simple.
Even without any untrusted advice, they're just
like a binary tree of multiplication gates.
This is called a "grand product".
If you want --
If you just want to compute the product of
all entries of x, I don't need any advice.
I'm just going to multiply them
together in a tree and that's it.
Tracy: I see.
Justin: And that's exactly where
we're starting to see GKR get applied.
Tracy: Okay.
Justin: Let's actually just see a binary
tree multiplication gates real fast.
So we have x₁, x₂, x₃, x₄.
So we want to multiply these four things together.
So here's our circuit that does it.
Okay.
And the way the GKR Protocol works is like,
the prover is going to send the
value of this claimed output gate.
Tracy: Yep.
Justin: The verifier doesn't trust that claim,
so it's going to apply the Sum-Check
Protocol to reduce the claim about the output
to a claim about the gates
feeding into the output.
Now, in this tiny picture, like,
you can compute those gates,
you know, the circuit's so small,
maybe the verifier is willing to actually
compute those gate values itself,
and check the claim.
Tracy: But if this tree is very large.
Justin: The verifier doesn't
want to do all the work
to compute the values of the
gates feeding into the output.
So you're not happy with that,
just as the verifier wasn't happy
at the end of round one of Sum-Check,
it continued to the next round.
So you'd apply Sum-Check again to reduce a
claim about these gates to a claim about --
Well, in this case, it's the input,
but in general would be like the next layer
and the next layer and the next layer.
So for this grand product context anyway,
the proof size, you wind up applying the
Sum-Check Protocol once per layer of the circuit,
but there's logarithmically, many
layers of the circuit log in the
number of things we're multiplying together.
So the proof size is log squared.
Okay.
Tracy: I see. Okay.
Justin: Which is, in practice,
maybe 10 kilobytes-ish.
So not as short as like KZG proofs, but
much shorter than FRI proofs or something.
Tracy: Yeah. Pretty efficient.
Justin: That's the high level. And --
Yeah, whether or not this is
a major speed up over Spartan,
there's sort of a trade-off between the
verifier cost compared to Spartan are going up,
but the prover costs are potentially going down
largely because you don't have to
commit to the interior gate values.
Tracy: And for some circuits
that trade-off changes
because you have to have a whole bunch of
additional witness or advice in
order to evaluate the circuit.
Justin: Right.
So if you weren't just producting all your
inputs together and that's all the circuit did,
it might be --
You might not have a way to keep the circuit small
without having lots and lots
of untrusted advice inputs.
And then you might as well just
commit to everything at that point.
But these grand products seem to
be at the heart of efficient SNARKs
and it's like perfectly suited.
You don't need any untrusted advice.
Other comments are -- well, the way
the grand products tend to get applied,
the stuff being producted are random values,
which tends to make them
very expensive to commit to.
Literally an order of magnitude or more costlier
to commit to than if they were "small values".
Tracy: I see.
Justin: And so cutting out those commitments
the way Spartan would have had you do,
can really save the prover a lot of time.
And then there are sort of hybrid approaches,
where you can get kind of most of
the proof size benefits of Spartan
without major slowdown relative to GKR.
And then --
Yeah. So -- so Spartan is potentially a slower
prover than GKR, but definitely smaller proofs.
And then anything that doesn't use Sum-Check,
in my view, tends to be slower than either.
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: Because not only do they commit to
the interior gate values of the circuit,
they commit to a bunch of other things as well.
Often there are quotient polynomials
arising which are expensive to compute,
might or might not be explicitly committed,
and just you avoid all of that with Sum-Check.
Tracy: Cool.
Tracy: Yeah.
The quotient polynomial on
Plonk is particularly large
because the degree of the gates that feed into it.
Justin: Yeah. That's right.
I think Plonk does have commitment costs
that grow with the degree of the constraints.
There are other univariate SNARKs
that don't necessarily have that,
but there's still some quotient
polynomial somewhere arising.
Yeah. And so there's a lot of
components to these systems
and I view the amount of committed data as like
a first order measure of prover efficiency.
But it's definitely not the
case that you want to minimize
the amount of committed data at all costs. Right?
It's definitely better to commit
quotient and remainder than to
have a circuit do division in the circuit. Right?
Tracy: Yeah.
Justin: So it can be a delicate balance.
But I think the SNARKs that are most
popular today are too far to one side,
if what you care about is prover time.
And if you go way too far to the Sum-Check
side, your circuit would be huge.
And so you want to be somewhere in the middle.
But there's a --
You know, a happy medium that
I think we're finding now.
Tracy: Cool. Awesome.
That's a great overview.
Thanks for taking the time!
Justin: Thanks for having me!